Did you know that your health insurance
policy
can also cover delivery charges, including C-section and
normal deliveries? You
can also get vaccination coverage and newborn coverage under this plan.
However, this isn't possible with all health insurance plans,
as only a few offer
maternity
coverage. Therefore, in today's video,
I'm going to compare India's top five maternity
coverage health insurance policies. We'll detail
which plan offers
coverage for how much delivery charges,
how long will it take to
receive this coverage, the waiting period for each plan,
and the
terms and conditions related to maternity so
you don't have to pay anything at the time of claim. If
you're considering a health insurance policy with maternity coverage,
today's video will make your decision even
smarter. Let's not delay
and quickly start the video.
Friends, the first plan on this list is
Star Health Insurance's Assure
plan.  You also get maternity coverage. The
limit for claiming maternity-related expenses
is 10% of your basic sum insured, which is
10% of your insured amount. You
can claim for delivery charges or related expenses, but can you
claim them from day one? This is
not the case. For this, you will have to complete a waiting period of
24 months. From the day
you purchase the policy,
you will not be able to file any maternity or related
claim for the next 24 months, nor will the company
entertain that claim. There
is no defined waiting period between subsequent deliveries, i.e., if you have claimed a claim for one delivery, and the next delivery, whenever you
plan a new member of your family, or plan a baby, there is no
waiting period in between.
What are these pre- and post-natal expenses from the company?
See, when a baby is conceived,
whatever expenses are incurred between the mother becoming pregnant and the child's birth.  You have to
see a doctor, there are sonograms, there are
ultrasounds, there are blood tests, these are
called prenatal expenses,
and the expenses incurred after delivery are
called postnatal expenses,
so you can also cover such expenses
under this plan. Now what are the conditions
for maternity coverage?
Both the parents must be in this policy for
24 consecutive months. It is
not that this policy was in your individual name,
you covered it for one year and the
next year your wife comes under this policy,
and then you will
not be able to claim the delivery charges in the next year.
Both the parents
must be in this policy for 24 consecutive months, only then you will be
able to claim maternity-related expenses. Pre and post hospitalization
expenses are never covered under maternity.
New born baby cover.
What is this? See, after the birth of the child,
you can add him to the policy after 91 days,
but if there is any medical
complication between the birth of the child and the time of birth
Between the age of 90 days, you
can cover him under the Newborn Baby Cover,
but for that too, the insurance company has
given some sub-limits under which
you will get treatment. If your sum insured
is between ₹ 5 lakh to ₹ 1 lakh, then
you will get a Newborn Baby Cover of ₹ 1 lakh. If
your sum insured is between ₹ 1 lakh to ₹ 2 crore,
then you can take a Newborn Baby Cover of ₹ 1 lakh, that is, if
any
complication occurs to the child or their
mother after delivery, then you can get treatment under this coverage.
What are the conditions? The first condition
is that if the maternity claim has been approved under this policy, only then
you can claim Newborn Baby Cover. And the
mother, that is, the
mother of this child who is born, must be in this policy for 12 months continuously. The
next point comes for taking any Newborn Baby Cover.
Friends,
assisted reproduction treatment under this plan. Now the
lifestyle has become such that naturally baby
Many times, if conception does not happen, one has to resort to assisted
reproduction treatment techniques like IVF.
This treatment can also be covered under this plan. Let us
know the conditions
associated with assisted reproduction treatment.
First, there
is a waiting period.
You will not be able to file any claim for assisted reproduction treatment for 24 months after purchasing the policy. Only
one treatment cycle will be covered in a year. If
one IVF procedure is done
and it is unfortunately unsuccessful, then the
second cycle of this treatment in the same year will
not be covered. Next year, you will
get coverage for the second treatment. The
amount of coverage you can avail will
depend on your sum insured. If your sum insured is ₹5 lakh, then
you can avail coverage for assisted reproduction treatment worth ₹1 lakh.
If your sum insured is between ₹10 lakh and
₹1 lakh, then you can
claim for assisted reproduction treatment worth ₹1 lakh.  If your
sum insured is between ₹1 lakh and ₹2 crore, then
you will be able to claim assisted reproductive treatment worth ₹1 lakh.
If we talk about child vaccination, that is,
vaccination of the child, then
you do not get coverage for it under the Star Asher plan.
Friends, the second name in the list of best maternity plans is TA
AIG's Medicare Premier Plan. The
coverage you get under this plan,
i.e., how many delivery expenses you
can claim, is linked to your sum insured.
If your sum insured is up
to ₹1 lakh, then you can claim ₹5,000,000 for a boy child
and ₹1,000,000 for a girl child. If your sum insured is
between ₹75 lakh and ₹3 crore, then
you can claim ₹1 lakh for a boy child and ₹1,20,000 for a girl child
for delivery expenses. Talking about the waiting period,
it is 4 years.
You can claim any delivery expense within 48 months of purchasing the policy.  You will
not be able to file a maternity-related claim.
Pre- and post-natal expenses are
not covered under the TAAG Medicare Premier Plan. Neither pre- nor
post-hospital expenses are covered under this plan. These are
not covered at all in any maternity coverage. If we
talk about new-born baby cover, which is
called delivery complications cover in this plan,
you can cover it,
but there are limits in it. If your sum
insured is up to ₹1 lakh, then ₹1000000. If
your sum insured is between ₹75 lakh and ₹3 crore, then
₹2500000
for a boy child and ₹15000 for a girl
child. But there are some conditions too, which are also
important to know. If the maternity claim has been
accepted in this plan, only then you
can claim for vaccination. The
child whose vaccination you are claiming should be
added to this policy, that is,
he should be in this policy as a member
and this is a lifetime cover.  The limit is 10000
for a boy child and 15000 for a girl
child. This is not the limit of one policy or one year,
it is the limit for the lifetime of the entire policy.
You can claim for vaccination
if you fulfill the terms and conditions. So
friends, the third name in this list
is Niva B Aspire Plan, which is the
latest plan of this company, in which
your maternity benefits have been covered under Miracle Benefit.
First of all, let's
talk about coverage, that is, how much rupees
you can claim,
you can claim from the sum in short of your Miracle Benefit,
how much it will be, it will be according to your sum
insured. If
you have taken a policy of ₹ 5 lakh, then there
is a Miracle Benefit of ₹ 000 on a policy of
₹ 5000000, there is a
Miracle Benefit of ₹ 1000000 on a policy of ₹
12000 on a policy of ₹ 10 lakh  If the
sum
insured is ₹15 lakhs, then the sum insured is ₹2000000, and if the sum insured is ₹50 lakhs to 1
crores, then the sum insured is ₹2500000. You will
not be able to file any maternity related claim, that is, you will
not be able to use the Miracle Sum Insured. Will pre and
post natal charges be covered?
Only pre natal charges will be covered, including
doctor's consultations,
sonograms, blood tests, etc. You
can cover them. If your maternity claim is
accepted by the company, then
what are the conditions? The biological mother must be covered in this policy, that is, the
mother who
gives birth to the child must be a member of this policy
and only the Miracle Sum
Insured can be used for delivery or any
associated expenses.
Pre and post hospital
expenses are not covered. New born baby
cover is covered in this but  You will be able to use only
your sum in the Miracle Sum In Scheme.
Apart from that,
what other extra coverages do you get?
Vaccines for expecting mothers, i.e., the
vaccination expenses of pregnant mothers can also be covered under the Miracle Sum In Scheme.
Surrogacy delivery by a
surrogate mother, i.e.,
if the child is delivered by someone else, then
you can also get that coverage under it.
IVF and assisted
reproduction treatments can also be
claimed under the Miracle Benefit.
Treatment of infertility is also included in this plan,
and the charges of legally
adopting a child, i.e., if you legally
adopt a child, then its expenses can also be
covered under this plan. Now,
what are the conditions? You will have to
take all these coverages from the Miracle Benefit itself, and I think that is
very less, brother, there is a benefit of ₹ 000 for every ₹ 1 lakh.
Suppose a policy of ₹ 1 lakh, then
you  You get a miracle benefit of ₹1 but the
company says that this is not a one time miracle
benefit of ₹1500000. You can carry it forward.
Suppose you do
not use any feature of the miracle benefit for one year, then
it will be added to the miracle benefit of the next year and that addition can be carried forward to the
next year as well.
What will be the maximum limit depends on the
age at which you have taken this policy and which
variant you have chosen because according to that, the
number of times your miracle
benefit can increase is decided.
For example, suppose your age is 25 years at the
time you have bought this policy and the
variant you have taken is Titanium Plus
i.e. top variant, then you can use the miracle benefit up
to 10 times
but that will happen after 10 years.
Now, what is this limit for each plan?
At what age, how many times will
you get the miracle benefit.
I have made a detailed video for this separately.
I am
giving you the link of the description menu for this plan. You can
go there and
shortlist whichever plan you
think is right for you and watch its detailed
video because you also need to know about the other features,
apart from these maternity,
you can check the other features in the video detail from there so that you can know about
other terms and conditions and coverages of this plan from there.
Now let's
move on to our next plan. Now
friends, let's talk about ICICI's
Advantage Plan. Under this plan, you get maternity
coverage, but
you will have to take As an Add-on within this plan, that is, the
company provides optional cover, if you want, you
can add it to the policy. Now,
since today we are talking about maternity features, if you
add As an Add-on to this policy, let's
understand what coverage you will get. First of all,
coverage means how much money you
can claim for delivery expenses, that is
your sum insured.  10% means
10% of your sum insured or maximum ₹1
lakh. What is the maximum capping among these two? It is
₹1 lakh. You will be able to claim up to 10% of your sum insured. The
waiting period
is ₹1000 per month. After purchasing the policy for the first time,
you will not be able to file any claim related to maternity for the next 9 months. Be it
pre and post hospitalization expenses
or pre and post natal expenses, these are
not covered under this plan.
What is the condition? To avail maternity coverage, the mother
's age should be between 18 to 45 years
and you will be able to avail this addon only with a 3-year
long term policy. That is,
when you buy a 1-year policy,
you cannot choose this addon.
When you buy a 3-year policy, you
can avail this maternity addon as an extra optional
feature. But suppose
you have taken this addon for the first 3 years and you have not availed any
maternity addon.  If you do not file a claim, then if
you buy a long term policy for the next 3 years
and take a maternity cover under it, then the
extra
premium for maternity will not be charged from you again
because the maternity premium you paid for the first time has
not been used. So, in the next long
term policy, the maternity premium will
not be charged from you. The normal premium will be
charged from you. But you will get a
3-year policy along with a newborn
baby cover. This is also an
optional coverage. How much coverage will you get?
You can cover twice the maternity coverage under newborn baby coverage.
This will be covered only
when your maternity claim is accepted by this company in
this plan. Only then will you get
newborn baby coverage or any other
claim. And the maternity should be within this plan, only then
you
can take newborn baby cover as an optional cover.
Talking about vaccination cover,
that is, you can also get vaccination cover. The child's vaccination
can also be covered up to 1 percent of the
sum.  1% of the sum insured or a
maximum limit of ₹1000000 will be covered. The
fifth plan that
we have shortlisted for maternity
is
Reliance 1. It is given because
not every insured needs maternity, so
some companies
offer it as an option, that whoever needs it can take it by paying
extra money and those who do
not need it can take the standard plan.
These five plans that I have told you are
one of the top selling plans of their companies, that is why
this
feature has been kept optional in some plans so that every customer does
not have to pay the premium for this add-on. First of all, let's talk about its coverage,
so you can choose whatever amount of maternity coverage you want between ₹1 lakh and ₹1
lakh. There
is also an option for waiting period of 12 months and
24 months. You can also choose this. There is a
waiting period of 12 months.  If you choose this,
your premium will increase slightly.
If you take a waiting period of 24 months
for maternity, your premium will
reduce slightly because the waiting period
is more. Will pre and post natal expenses be
covered? They will definitely be covered.
Pre natal expenses will be
covered from pregnancy till child birth
and post
natal expenses will be covered from delivery till the next one month. This plan will cover the
conditions. The mother's age should be between 18 to 45 years.
You will get this add-on only with a 3 year long term policy, that is, you
cannot take maternity add-on in this policy with a 1 year or 2 year policy.
You can also take new born baby cover under this plan.
Its coverage is up to ₹1 lakh, that is, if any complication occurs
between the birth of the child and 90 days,
then
you can take coverage up to ₹1 lakh. The
condition under this plan is if  Only if the maternity claim has been
accepted,
you can avail coverage for a new born baby in this plan
and
this coverage will work till the baby is 90 days old. Now let's talk about
vaccination coverage, that will also be
covered in this plan but only till the
baby is 90 days old.
Any vaccination done before that will be
covered. After completing the 90 days age,
vaccination coverage will not be available.
This can be availed only if the maternity claim has been
accepted in this plan and
which vaccinations will be covered are
visible on the screen right now.
All these vaccinations will be covered till the child is 90 days old in
this plan.
Now friends, you have understood the maternity coverage of all these five plans,
I have told you in sequence. Now
what I will do is compare each feature across the plans
and find out
which feature is better in which plan and which
feature is lacking in any plan so that
you  You can get an idea from the comparison that which
plan has most of the features that are useful for you
and which plan does
not have the features that you need so that you can
take your decision smartly. The
first feature that comes is the sum insured,
that is, how much amount can you file a claim for.
If we talk about Star Assure, then the
sum insured is 10 per cent, which is a
decent amount. If you
take a policy of ₹1 lakh, then you get coverage of ₹1 lakh
under maternity benefits,
which is not a small amount and is decent.
If we talk about Ti IG Medicare Premier, then there are
separate sum insureds for ₹5000000 and ₹1 lakh and 0000 and ₹2000000, that is, for boy child and girl child, these are also
decent sum insured. If we consider the delivery charges, then let us
talk about
NV Aspire plan. There is a miracle in it.
You will be able to use only your sum assured within the benefit. Now, I
find a slight problem with this. If you are
planning delivery in 2 or 3 years and
if you want to use the entire scope of coverage, then
this sum insured will
fall a little short. Suppose you take a sum insured of ₹1 lakh, then the
benefit will be ₹1500000, that is, ₹1000000 in two years. The
maximum limit will depend on your
plan variant and your age. So,
somewhere in this, there is a
foundation that your sum
insured may not be sufficient
or considering its coverage, its
scope of coverage or the number of features and
benefits of Miracle Benefit,
I feel that this sum insured may
fall short. Talking about ICICI Advantage Plan,
10 percent of sum insured or
₹10 lakh is also quite sufficient.  Reliance is insured. There
is an option of ₹1 lakh or ₹1 lakh.
If we talk about maternity expenses, then if you
compare it with other health insurance plans, then you get decent coverage in this too.
Now comes the turn of the waiting period, that is,
after how much time can you claim these delivery
expenses? There is a
waiting period of 24 months in Starcare. There is a
waiting period of 48 months in AAG Medicare,
which is quite negative.
If you need maternity coverage after 4 years, then you
can take this plan, but if
you are planning before that,
then this plan will not be able to provide you coverage. There
is a waiting period of only 9 months in Niva B. You can choose a waiting period of 9 months in ICICI Advantage
and
reliance 1 or 24 months. So, if we
talk about maternity
plans, then a waiting period of 12 to 24 months is
considered decent. Any
waiting period beyond that becomes a little
longer.  For example, in Tata EIG's
Medicare plan, you are getting a
waiting period of 48 months, so this is a bit
negative. For this plan, pre and
post natal expenses, that is, the expenses from getting pregnant
till child birth and
after child birth, will
come under post natal, so these expenses will be
covered under Star Ashar plan, these are
not covered under Tata Medicare. Only
prenatal expenses and anti natal expenses
are covered under Niva Bappa Aspire, that is, the expenses from pregnancy
till child birth will be covered,
but only Miracle Sum
Insured or ICICI Advantage plan,
this is not covered, that is, pre and
post natal expenses are not covered.
Reliance 1
These charges will be covered only for the next one month after delivery,
so according to this, the
coverage of Star Health Insurance seems to be the best in this.
Talking about new born baby coverage,
how much coverage is available,
in Star Ashar you have the option of sum in  According to short, the sum assured of ₹
22 lakh and ₹1 lakh
in Medicare is very less. It is related to ₹0000 and ₹2500000,
so this amount will not be sufficient in ₹225000.
In case of any complication, in the NM Aspire
plan, you will have to use Miracle Sum Insurance,
which already
covers the maternity expenses, that is the big thing.
In the IIC Advantage plan,
you will get two times your maternity insurance, which is more than
sufficient.
Reliance 1 lakh is covered, that is,
in NM Aspire, because
you have to adjust the maternity amount from this sum assured, so in
these two plans,
I feel that the coverage of newborn baby is a
little less amount wise. Assisted
reproduction treatment means the baby is
not conceived naturally. If
a family conceives a baby with the help of a doctor, then
you get that coverage in Star Aspire.  ₹ 1
lakh, 2 lakh and ₹ 1 lakh depending on your sum assured.
However, there will be a waiting period of 24 months.
This coverage is not available under Medicare premium. However, there is
coverage under Aspire plan.  But it has to be
used only through Miracle Sum Insured. ICC
Advantage Plan and
Reliance 1 Haj and ₹10000 if a
boy is born and if a girl is
born then you can take a lifetime limit of ₹1 haj
for vaccination. If the
maternity claim is accepted
then
only the vaccination of the expecting mother
is covered under Niva Bappa Aspire plan but that too from Miracle
Sum Insured. Under ICC Advantage plan
you can claim up to % of sum insured up
to a maximum of ₹1000000.
If the maternity claim is accepted then Reliance covers the cost of vaccination up to 1
day. So the
vaccines till that time which are listed and which are
visible to you on the screen right now can be
covered. So these
points which I have mentioned one by one are covered for every plan.
Sum Insured Waiting Period  Pre
and post natal expenses, new born
baby coverage, gestational production treatment and
vaccination, these are the
most common coverages related to maternity. Now after
looking at this overall comparison, I feel that if we
look at the sum insured as per the newborn baby coverage,
pre and post natal expenses, then
I feel that the Star Asher
plan
gives you standard coverage in every respect. There is a waiting period of 24 months,
which is also not much.
You can claim the sum insured for maternity on 10%. There
is coverage of ₹ 2 to ₹ lakh for the new born baby as well. Assisted reproduction
treatment is also covered.
Everything else under Medicare Premier is fine
but one thing is that the waiting period is more. The
coverage of 48 months for newborn baby is also very
less. There is no facility for assisted reproduction treatment also.
Bappa Aspire Plan is
one of my favorite plans if the
sum insured for the miracle benefit of maternity is there.
If they had given more,
according to their scope of coverage, now
you are getting 10% coverage in this but
how much is that summary sum, 3000, 5000, 10000, 12000,
which you will have to collect for a long time,
then you will have to use it. Now
when does a person have to take maternity coverage?
When he is young, he gets married,
starts a family, then it is not like that, he will
wait for 10 years for miracle benefit,
after that he will get the claims related to it.
This sum insured, immediate sum
insured, if you had got a good one, it would have been even
better in Nipa Aspire plane,
but the coverage is quite good, but the
sum insured is not enough.
I feel it is like if you take a child to a fair
and tell him that you
can eat burger, pizza, ice cream, everything,
but you have only 20 rupees,
you will have to adjust from this, otherwise
you will have to come to the fair next year when you
have 40 rupees, otherwise next year you will lose 20 rupees.  If you
reach ₹1,
I think the sum insured is a
bit narrowed down, and its range is quite
low. I also find the IIC Advantage plan in the Niva v Aspire plan to be
decent,
but it doesn't cover pre- and postnatal
charges. If
you have to include this as an add-on to the policy,
you may have to pay extra money.
[Music] You can choose a
sum in short of reliance 1 or ₹1 lakh. You
can also choose a waiting period of 12 or 24 months for delivery charges.
This plan is quite flexible. Pre-
and postnatal expenses are also covered, meaning postnatal
expenses are covered up to 1 month.
Prenatal is already covered, and you get
newborn baby coverage up to ₹1 lakh. You
also get some vaccination coverage. If
you choose
reliance 1, that means
you will have to pay extra money over and above the standard plan. Overall, through
this comparison,
you have got the details of each plan linked to the mainnet.
Or have you gotten an idea of
how much maternity benefits
you get under these plans,
how much you can claim for each facility, and what
conditions the company has imposed?
However, a health insurance
plan includes many features beyond maternity,
such as a room rent
limit, a cumulative bonus, and a
retirement benefit. It's important to know and understand these as well.
Therefore, you can find a
detailed video of the maternity coverage of whichever plan you prefer or whichever plan you shortlist for your maternity coverage.
You
can go there and watch the entire video
to understand the overall package offered by this plan. This is
crucial because maternity
coverage is only a part of the overall coverage;
it's not the entire plan. So,
friends, I hope this video has added some value to your research or effort to choose a
maternity health insurance plan,
and it has helped you in many ways.  Doubts related to maternity coverage must have been
cleared. If you also
feel the same and agree with me, then
you
can like this video to show your support and your love.
And if you
want to be a part of our community whose only aim
is to bring insurance awareness for you
so that none of your
claims are rejected due to lack of information, you do not take any wrong decision
related to insurance and every
rupee that
you have invested in the insurance policy can be
fully utilized, then you
can also subscribe to this channel. I
welcome you all very much to my family.
So friends, now please allow me i.e.
Harvinder Singh, I will
meet you in the next video. Till then, take
care of yourself, stay happy and stay healthy.
Jai Hai.